Guide to the Archives of Irish America Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians AIA.046
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians
1903-2008
1970-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.046
3.25 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
The Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH) is a Catholic, Irish-American fraternal Organization founded in New York City in 1836. Active across the United States, the Order seeks to aid the newly-arrived Irish, both socially and economically. The AOH in America is partitioned into Divisions, County Boards, and State Boards, and is governed by a National Board elected every two years. The Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians (LAOH) is an associate organization of the AOH but was not officially recognized until 1894 in Omaha, Nebraska. The LAOH recognizes values and missions similar to AOH, and they often conduct activities together. The Records of the Ancient Order of Hibernians primarily document the activities of those divisions in the New York City region, as well as some of the National Boards. The records largely include programs from events, mostly dinners and conventions, but also contain newsletters, correspondence, press releases, circulars and publications.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
The Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH) is a Catholic, Irish American fraternal Organization founded in New York City in 1836. The Order traces its roots back to similar societies that existed in Ireland for over 300 years beginning in the mid-16th century. While the AOH now resides in the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom, the United States AOH is a separate and much larger organization.
Like its early Irish predecessors, the AOH was formed to protect the welfare of its Irish-Catholic members. On May 4, 1836, the AOH in America was founded at New York's St. James Church by men emulating these Irish societies, to protect the clergy and churches from the violent American nativists who attacked Irish Catholic immigrants and Church property. At the same time the vast influx of Irish Immigrants fleeing Ireland's Great Hunger in the late 1840's prompted a growth in many Irish societies in the USA - the largest of which was and continues to be the AOH.
Active across the United States, the Order seeks to aid the newly-arrived Irish, both socially and economically. The many Divisions and club facilities located throughout the U.S. have traditionally been among the first to welcome new Irish immigrants. Here, the Irish culture -- art, dance, music, and sports are fostered and preserved. The AOH has been at the forefront of issues concerning the Irish, such as immigration reform, economic incentives (both domestic and in Ireland), the human rights issues addressed in the MacBride Legislation, Right-To-Life, and a peaceful and just solution to the issues that divide Ireland.
The AOH in America is partitioned into Divisions, County Boards, and State Boards, and is governed by a National Board elected every two years. The Division is the basic unit in the Order, and membership in a Division is membership in the Order. Even County, State, and National Officers, maintain membership in a local Division. Annual dances, concerts, and parades sponsored by all levels of the Order raise millions for charity, while providing a showcase for the positive contributions of the Irish to every walk of American life.
The Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians is an associate organization of the AOH but was not officially recognized until 1894 in Omaha, Nebraska. The LAOH recognizes values and missions similar to AOH, and they often conduct activities together. Originally called the "Daughters of Erin," the LAOH has changed names several times up to 1984 when it became the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians.
Sources:
http://www.aoh.com/pages/about.html
http://www.ladiesaoh.com./whoarewe.html
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through donations, gifts, and through ongoing collecting by Archives of Irish America staff. Many items in this collection were donated by John T. Ridge. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2012.029 and 2012.036.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AIA 016 Irish Immigration Reform Movement AIA 003 County Societies Collection AIA 056 United Irish Counties Association AIA 057 Emerald Isle Society
Missing Title
County Societies Collection AIA 003
United Irish Counties Association AIA 056
Emerald Isle Society AIA 057
Archives of Irish America Manuscript Collection 006
Scope and Content Note
The Ancient Order of Hibernians Collection primarily documents the activities of those divisions in the New York City region, as well as some of the National Boards. The majority of the collection consists of records dating from the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s. The records include programs from events, mostly dinners and conventions, as well as newsletters, correspondence, press releases, circulars and publications. Many of the regional divisions' files contain material from both the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH) and the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians (LAOH), especially pertaining to those occasions when the two collaborated.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
One photograph was donated by John T. Ridge in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.117.
Programs (documents).; Clippings (information artifacts); Circular letters.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Newsletters.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Social life and customs.; Correspondence.; Ancient Order of Hibernians
- Bronx County Board - Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH), 1992; 293993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bronx County Board - AOH Division 8, 1944-1946; 294293 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bronx County Board - AOH Division 9, 1982, 1987; 294294 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bronx County Board - Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians (LAOH), Apr 1995; 294295 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Kings County Board - AOH, 1973-1994; 294296 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- King's County Board - AOH Meeting Minutes, 1952-1966; 590680 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- King's County Board - AOH Meeting Minutes, 1966-1969; 590681 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Kings County Board - Division 23 (Greenpoint, Brooklyn) Minutes, 1903-1921; 590654 (Box 6)
- Kings County Board - AOH Division 35, 1989-1992; 294297 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Kings County Board - LAOH, Feb 1989; 294298 (Box 1, Folder 7, Box AIAXOS001, Folder 1)
- Nassau County Board - AOH, 1988; 294299 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- National Board - AOH, 1982-1994, undated; 294300 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- National Board - Convention, 1972; 294301 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- National Board - Convention, 1986, 1988; 294302 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- National Board - Convention, 1972, 1986; 294303 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- National Board - Convention, Jul 1990; 294304 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Board - Dinner Dance, May 1976; 294305 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- National Board - Irish National Hunger Commemoration Committee, 1994-1996; 294307 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National Board - AOH and LAOH "The Irish Influence in the American Labor Movement", 1985; 294306 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- National Board - AOH and LAOH National Convention, 1990; 294308 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- National Board - LAOH, 1978-1994; 294309 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The National Hibernian Digest, 2008; 294310 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- New York County Board - AOH, 1967, 1987-1995; 294311 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New York County Board - AOH Annual Dinner Dance, 1972-1975; 294312 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- New York County Board - AOH Annual Dinner Dance, 1976-1979; 294313 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York County Board - AOH Annual Dinner Dance, Nov 1996; 294314 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- New York County Board - AOH Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance, Oct 1995; 294315 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 3, 1977-1993; 294316 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 4, 1970, 1989-1997; 294317 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 4, 1998, 2003; 294318 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 5, 1989; 294319 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 9, 1999-2002; 294320 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- New York County Board - AOH Division 29, 1998; 294321 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Cocktail Party and Luncheon, 1984-1988; 294322 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Cocktail Party and Luncheon, 1989-1991; 294323 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Cocktail Party and Luncheon, 1992-1993; 294324 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Cocktail Party and Luncheon, 1998-1999; 294325 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Division 29, 1998, 2003; 294326 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- New York County Board - AOH and LAOH Reception-Dance, 1984; 294327 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- New York State Board - AOH and LAOH Convention, 1972, 1985; 294328 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- New York State Board - AOH and LAOH Convention, Jul 1987; 294329 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- New York State Board - AOH and LAOH Convention, Jul 1989; 294330 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- New York State Board - AOH and LAOH Convention, 1991, 1995; 294331 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- New York State Board - AOH Newsletters, 1988; 294332 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- New York State Board - AOH President's Testimonial Dinner, 1987-2002; 294333 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Non-New York AOH Divisions, 1953-1999; 294334 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Queens County AOH and LAOH Communion Breakfast photograph, 1955 (Box Shared Tamiment 016, Folder 5)
- Queens County Board - AOH, 1986-1990; 294335 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Queens County Board - AOH and LAOH Joint Activities, 1987-1993; 294336 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Queens County Board - LAOH, 1984-1993; 294337 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Richmond County Board - AOH Division 1, 1996; 294338 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Rockland County Board - AOH, 1988-2000; 294339 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Westchester County Boards - AOH and LAOH, 1991; 294340 (Box 5, Folder 10)